<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Liberty of conscience explicated and vindicated, and the just limits betwixt it and authority sacred and civil, cleared</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48375</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12964893</idno>
  <idno type="VID">96113</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264189076</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1964</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3710</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12964893</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48375)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96113)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 388:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Liberty of conscience explicated and vindicated, and the just limits betwixt it and authority sacred and civil, cleared</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Lawrence ... and are to be sold by Richard Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Licensed, March 26, 1689"</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Liberty of conscience --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96113:1"/>
            <p>LIBERTY OF CONSCIENCE Explicated and Vindicated, AND THE Just Limits Betwixt it and AUTHORITY, SACRED and CIVIL, Cleared.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Licensed,</hi> March 26. 1689.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>John Lawrence,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> over against the <hi>Poultrey-Counter,</hi> and are to be Sold by <hi>Richard Baldwin</hi> in the <hi>Old-Baily.</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:96113:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96113:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Liberty of Conscience</hi> EXPLICATED and VINDICATED.</head>
            <p>THE sharp Contests between Authority, Sacred and Civil, and Liberty of Conscience in matter of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the sad Consequences thence arising, hath made the violent on both sides strain their Wits, to maintain or promote their Interest; the sober and moderate have been pleased with neither extreme, yet few of them have used half so much diligence to point out the right Path, as these in either extreme have used to stray from it; there is now a fair occasion of a happy Accord, when all good men are sensible of the evil of the imposing the profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion or practice of things unnecessary for Holiness or Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and when there are so just and unprejudicate Judges. So that there only remains to be cleared, how far the Church is obliged to require of these in her communion, and how far they may yield obedience with a good conscience, and how far civil Authority is obliged to use punishment or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action upon account of Religion. The first Christian Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod held at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> laid this sober and solid ground; <hi>It seemed good to the Holy Ghost; and unto us, to lay upon you no greater burden than these necessary things.</hi> They have also there determined what they account necessary things, saying, <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asmuch as we have heard, that certain which went out from us have troubled you with words subverting your Souls.</hi> So that these things are only necessary to be avoided which subvert Souls; and these things are only necessary to be press'd which are necessary to be believed and professed for obtaining Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that is necessary, <hi>necessitate Medii,</hi> and not all which are necessary, <hi>necessitate Precepti;</hi> these things that are neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96113:3"/>
               <hi>necessitate Medii,</hi> are such wherein not only error, but ignorance is not safe; such as <hi>he that comes to God, must be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that he is, and that he is a rewarder of these that diligently seek him. There is no Name given under Heaven by which Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can come but by the Name of Jesus; without Faith it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible to please God; without Holiness no man can see God; who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever will be willing to become Christ's disciple, must be willing to be baptized in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost.</hi> Not by these Names only, but by their Offices towards the Disciples, the free election of the Father, the redemption of the Son, by his incarnation, suffering and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to Divine Justice, and the sanctification of the Holy Ghost. These are the Terms of Communion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in Christ's Commission to his Apostles, and to their Successors, Ministers of the Gospel, which is necessarily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported when he said, <hi>Lo, I am with you to the end of the world.</hi> But there is further required of these Ministers than of the Disciples, for they are ordered to teach them all things whatsoever Christ hath commanded. It is no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>superable task to find out the things that are necessary to be believ'd for obtaining Salvation.</p>
            <p>Church-men have been too apt to state the Question, what they may command, and not what they must command, for obtaining the Communion of the Church in all Divine Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, which ought to be refused to none who in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of charity should be esteemed to be in the favour of God and in the way of Salvation.</p>
            <p>If these who pretend to be Disciples, do hold Opinions evidently inconsistent with the means of salvation, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be esteemed to believe these necessary means which is not to be stretched to far distant consequences, which ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary capacities cannot perceive.</p>
            <p>A main ground of the disquiet of Christians, of the breach of Christian Communion, of Brotherly Kindness, and of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution, hath been the imposing of more to be profess'd and practis'd, as necessary for salvation, than is truly necessary, and the imposers have been the true cause of Schism, though ordinarily they cried out against those whom they chased away as Schismaticks.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96113:3"/>
            <p>It is an ordinary defence, that their being turned out, compelled or punished, was through their own fault, in being obstinate against clear light holden forth by the Church, and therefore they could not pretend Persecution. Nothing can be more frivolous and fallacious than this, for on that ground a few learned and pregnant Spirits might condemn and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secute a whole Church, on pretence, that they were obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and had sufficient light shewn them, but that they shut their eyes against it, and could not answer the Arguments adduced or extricate themselves, but obstinacy must be that only which is evident to every capacity, or otherwise there behoved to be as many Rules of Faith and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners as there are several degrees of Judgment; whereas there can be only two, one for the Flock, another for the Pastors, who must so lead the Flock, that the weakest Lamb be not left, nor any division made in the Flock to drive them by parcels, and as they have strength.</p>
            <p>It hath been a great occasion of Schism and Persecution, that there hath been only one Confession for a whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Church, both for the Flock and their Pastors ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily stuff'd with scholastick and obstruse Terms, and the discussing of intricate Questions, whereas there ought to be one for the Flock, containing only things necessary for Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and another for the Pastors, of things convenient to be known, and perswaded by Teachers, but not imposed, for it is the duty of Teachers to explain and clear all that is revealed, but if the plurality could impose their interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon the rest, and require their approbation, what dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>simulation and persecution behoved to be amongst the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors themselves, there being such a multitude of various in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations of many places in Scripture, would the major part think it sufficient to say, that they had holden forth sufficient light, and that the rest were obstinate, with what countenance then can they use that reason against the Vulgar.</p>
            <p>The Pastoral Confession may be more easily determined than the Vulgar to be the Catholick Doctrine of the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal Christian Church, that is, the Doctrine which all Christian National Churches do hold, which easily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by the Confessions of Faith, shewing evidently enough
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96113:4"/> in what things they all agree, and what is peculiar to any National Church.</p>
            <p>There are but Four National Christian Churches in Christendom, the Greek Church, whereof the Muscovitish is only in Christendom, the Roman Church, the Church that holds the Augustan Confession, which name them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves the Evangelick Church, and are commonly called Lutherans, and the Reformed Church. These two last are the National Churches of divers Kingdoms and States, which are not united, but have several Confessions, wherein are intermixed the Form of Government, Ceremonies, and Discipline, but Confessions of Faith are only Matters of Faith and doctrinal, different from these; and hardly will any man be so peremptory as to say, that the Form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment or Discipline, or Ceremonies, are to be asserted, as either to be of Divine Right, or to be against the same, but that it is sufficient for Pastors, much more for People, to live under them, though not to approve them further than that they are Ecclesiastical Constitutions. The <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptists, Arminians, Familists, Quakers,</hi> or the <hi>Socinians,</hi> have never been so far favoured by Divine Providence as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come National Churches.</p>
            <p>These National Churches have their peculiar Doctrines which are not Catholick, wherein the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> exceeds all others, yet are they so impudent as to pretend, that they have only the Catholick Doctrine, yea, that they are the only Church wherein Salvation can be found. The <hi>Greek</hi> Church hath also a multitude of peculiar Doctrines; And the <hi>Lutherans</hi> have too many, but far fewer than ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of these, and such as are not inconsistent with Faith and good Manners, which therefore should not exclude them from communion of the Reformed, though they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude them. They hold Consubstantiation, but without Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and therefore it is but a contemplative Error, as is their Opinion of Universal Grace purchased by Christ to all by their Birth or Baptism. The <hi>Church of England</hi> in their Liturgy professes not to doubt that all that are baptized, are truly regenerated, which were better forborn, because it is dubious, capable of two interpretations, for if all be taken collectively, it is neither a Catholick Doctrine, nor true, but
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96113:4"/> if it be meant distributively and in the judgment of charity, it importeth no more, than that there is no particular person whom they see or know to be lawfully baptized whom in the judgment of charity they do not believe to be regenerated.</p>
            <p>The reformed Churches are of all others the most truly Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick and Orthodox, for there is no Doctrine they hold concerning Faith and Holiness, which is not held by all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Christian Churches, with whom they differ only in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusing to believe the peculiar Doctrines which any of them do profess, and is rejected by others, which is evident as to the Churches of the Augustan Confession, and acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the sober and judicious of both sides, though many of them be extremely rigid, in denying communion to these, who believe not their peculiar Doctrines to be true, much less to be necessary to be believed for attaining Salvation, seeing they were not heard of in the Church for many hundred Years. Some of them also do attribute to the Reformed the superlapsarian way of explicating Election and Reprobation, which is in none of their Confessions, but held by a few both Popish and Protestant.</p>
            <p>If these two Confessions were made the measure of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehension, and of admission to, and exclusion from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Church, and of the Ministry of it, then were it easie to hold the Union of the Faith in the Bond of Peace, not only among the Members of the same Church, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween different Churches, though they held peculiar Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, if they did not hold them necessary to be believed, if they did not pervert the Faith and overthrow Souls, as doth the peculiar Doctrines of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> which has justly made all other Churches not only separate from them, but refuse communion with them. They were accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomed to make use of harsh Expressions of some Protestants as the Doctrine of their Confession, and did ever distort and mis-state the Controversies with Protestants, not suffering their Laity to read Protestant Books holding truly forth their own opinion, that they may keep them captive in error and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, whereof they are now of late become to be ashamed by the method of the Bishop of <hi>Condom,</hi> so much applauded by the Pope and many eminent Doctors of that Church, yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining evident grounds of separation from them.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:96113:5"/>
            <p>Seeing these Confessions ought to be the Rule, how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necessary, yea how hurtful must it be to require the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of any, of the different Forms of Government of the Church, or of the different ways of exercising discipline, even by these that are free to submit to them and live under them, though they do not approve them as the best way, or warranted by Divine Institution immediately, or by a power committed to the Church.</p>
            <p>But how much more intolerable is it to require as neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary to communion the approbation or practice of Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies not commanded in Scripture, upon pretence of Decency and Order, or of a Power given the Church to supply or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitute Ceremonies exclusive of Church-communion, though the Church, as all Societies may and must determine circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances, and prohibit what is undecent or disorderly, as being opposite to Civil Vertue, though not to the Christian Vertues; for who can pretend, that he who doth not behave in Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stures, Gestures, or Forms of Expression or Salutation, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the mode of the time and place in which he is, or is not affable, but sour and reserv'd, hath thereby sinned, much less is to be excluded from Christian communion. But if the Church shall assume a power to impose not only Civil but Religious Ceremonies, as outward Signs of inward Grace, or Christian Vertues, they may not only warrantably exceed the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> but even the number of the <hi>Jewish Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,</hi> which yet the Gospel acknowledges to be a Yoak of Bondage; if they can coyn one Religious Ceremony, why not two, and so forth to a Million?</p>
            <p>Should then the Church as the Terms of Communion im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose Forms of Preaching, or Prayer, as exclusive of all others, neither requiring the hability nor diligence of the Ministry or others, but which may be performed by every one who can comelily read, like the ordinary Service of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> though they may assist by examples of Prayer and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, they ought not to prescribe them as Rules or Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Communion of the Church or the Ministry.</p>
            <p>These things being thus cleared, the just limits of Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stical Authority and Liberty of Conscience will easily appear, for no Christian can pretend Liberty of Conscience, against the Principles of Christianity, evident and inculcated in the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96113:5"/> holy Scripture as necessary to salvation; and if they should, the Church may justly reject them as not being Christians, neither can the Ministers of the Church plead Liberty of Conscience in being a Minister of the Church, and yet refuse to teach the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Doctrine held by all National Christian Churches, and if they should, they may be justly rejected, or rejected from the Ministry of the Church, as being unfit to teach or rule a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Congregation, which yet will not exclude them from the communion of the Church as Members of the Flock, if they hold these things that are necessary for salvation.</p>
            <p>And on the other part, if the Church impose more, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conscience may justly be pleaded, not only because Liberty requires no other proof than that there is no sufficient proof for any contrary command, but more particularly and clearly it hath Christ's express warrant, saying, <hi>stand fast there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the liberty wherewith Christ hath made you free, and be not again intangled in the yoak of bondage,</hi> which certainly will not only extend to the Jewish Yoak of Bondage, but to any other Yoak that Christ hath not imposed.</p>
            <p>Liberty of Conscience, as it relates to civil authority, is quite another matter, than the Liberty to be pleaded with the Church, which hath nothing to do but with these that are Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, nor can govern any but these of their own Church; but as to civil authority, the question must be, what by the duty of their Office they are obliged to do in relation to Religion, and consequently what may be pleaded with them for liberty of Conscience in Religion, not only by Christians of a National Church, but even by other Christians, and these who are not Christians, for all Mankind have a natural Conscience, which by the light of Nature goeth a great length both to direct and correct them in their duty to God and Man, and none but God can oblige their Conscience, and consequently their Practice according to their Conscience, but in so far as they can convince them from Divine Principles in their minds by reason or reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</p>
            <p>It is a horrid Atheistical evasion to say, that the Conscience is free and subject to none, but God; as all thoughts are free, because no creature can know them, but the profession and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice are not free; and this pretence, that God having made man by his nature so passible a creature, that he is not able to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96113:6"/> bear the execrable inventions of men by lingring torture, though he could bear death, whereof there are so innumerable examples of the late Persecution of the <hi>Protestants</hi> in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Piemont,</hi> which overcome the power of Nature, and has made multitudes abjure their Religion and profess the contrary Superstition, both being against the light of their Conscience. This pretence is utterly inconsistent with the most terrible threatning that ever was used by Christ the Prince of Peace. <hi>Whosoever denieth me before men, him will I deny before my Father who is in heaven.</hi> It doth also encroach upon the Wisdom, Justice, and Goodness of God, who is always able to support these that trust in him, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the severest sufferings that ever he doth permit, whereof he hath given plentiful experiences, even in these cruel Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in which Death was sought for as hid treasure, but was refused, but, which is more, he has made Martyrs sing in the midst of consuming flames.</p>
            <p>The smart of persecution hath set mens wit a work to lay grounds for eviting it; and therefore some do deny all power of civil Soveraigns to constrain or punish upon account of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, their Commission being only as to Righteousness between Man and Man, and Sobriety of every Man. Upon which ground, Atheism, Blasphemy, and Contempt of God, should be no punishable Crimes, which would extinguish the clearest light of Nature, as well as of Revelation, and suppose God to have provided no Law in relation to himself.</p>
            <p>Others make the Rule and Measure of Civil Authority to be only the Light and Law of Nature, but not to extend to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituted and revealed Religion, and therefore can compel or punish none, but these that violate the clear light of Nature; but this pretence is likewise groundless, for the light of Nature doth not oblige as, or because it is the light of Nature, that is, because it's known by inbred or natural Principles, or because it is suitable to the Nature of Man, but as it is and manifests the Command of God, who writes it on Man's heart. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore where ever the Command of God doth appear, his Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerents are obliged no less to promote it than the light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in so far as they and their Subjects acknowledged Divine Principles known by revelation by them both, in so far as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the outward man, which is the only object of Civil Power for the common interest of Mankind, which is its chief de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96113:6"/> doth not admit that the civil powers should inquire into the secret thoughts of men, and therefore they are not obliged to discover these things that may take away their Life or Fame, unless they be otherways proven, or other proof be ready to prove them. And therefore <hi>Joshua</hi> did not abjure <hi>Achan</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess his crime, before it was proven by the Lot ordained by God; for then only it became a glorifying of God, not only to confess the fault, but to shew the truth of it, in bringing forth the <hi>Babylonish</hi> Garment and the Wedge of Gold hid in his Tent.</p>
            <p>Others hold, that the Civil Powers have no Warrant to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed against the Church or its Members, without an anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent Judgment of the Church, which is owned by the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> and hath been a main occasion of the congregational way of independent or insubordinate Congregations, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging no other Church-Authority, but what is in a single Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, which can meet and hear the Word of God toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, acknowledging no Superior Church-Authority. Yet Christ's Commission was not to the People, but to the Apostles and their Successors in Office, not severally, only in relation to their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Congregations, but also jointly; the Spirits of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets are subject to the Prophets, for God is not the God of Confusion, but of Order; which reason clears, that the subjection is not only in relation to the extraordinary gift of Prophesying. Yet that error doth not exclude from Church-communion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it concerns only Government. These gathered Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations are ordinarily good men, but the consequence of that way is exceeding bad; for if it should prevail, it would not only consist of the pious, but all others that retain the name of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, would set up such other Churches, wherein there would be nothing but outward formality at best, and such People, such Priests, wanting the good example of the pious pickt out in the first Congregations.</p>
            <p>There is another Error, which hath been the chief cause of Dissimulation or Persecution, that Soveraign Powers being Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, owning and establishing a National Church, ought to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel all their Subjects to hear Instruction, and after a competent time, to conform their Profession to the Church, or to be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as obstinate, and to be punished until they do conform. Thus the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> excited all Princes of their communion to compel Jews and Turks to become Christians, and them and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96113:7"/> all Christians to approve the whole Doctrine and Practice of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> whereby such execrable Hypocrisie and Cruelty hath been used in many Countries. The whole Jews in the Spanish Dominions were persecuted, and many of them run to other Countreys, and were there also destroyed to a vast number. The Mahometan Moors also were compelled to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess the Christian Religion, though they and their posterity for long time secretly practised their own superstition, which the whole World since hath abhorr'd.</p>
            <p>There is another prevailing Error a little narrower, That the Civil Powers are obliged to suffer none to have the Publick Worship of God, but these only of that Church which they approve, giving the rest only toleration within their own doors, without admitting any but three or four more, punishing all severely, who can be proven to have been present at any other Publick Worship, and forcing these who differ but from the Church in smaller matters to conform, as being no different Sect, but bogling Fanaticks, to be recovered by the Spur and Whip. The effect of this must be, that these have Zeal for the Publick Worship of God, and cannot comply with the Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Establishment, will be persecuted; and these who please to make pretence of unclearness, to joyn with the National Church, may, if they please, be Atheists, or at least have no Worship of God, publick or private.</p>
            <p>The Solemn Publick Worship of God, is the greatest Homage done him upon Earth, and is one indispensible Duty upon all Mankind, to avouch God in Publick Devotion according as he hath reveal'd the acceptable Way of his Worship, at least so far as the light of Nature convinces all that have the use of Reason. When the Church was but in one Nation, God required a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Worship of all the Males come to discretion several times of the year, being convened by the Temple; but when the Christian Church was to be diffused thorough the World, such a Solemnity of Publick Worship was not to be required, but that it should dwindle down into single Congregations, and the far greatest part of Nations be forced from it; if the Civil Powers should own that as the true Church which consisted but of few persons, it were the monstrousest change imaginable; and if that ground be good, the case may hold, seeing the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Powers must needs have their discretion what Profession
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96113:7"/> to own and establish. It is not long since the fiftieth part of <hi>Britain</hi> might have been the publick National Church, yea, less than the hundredth part; so that all the rest should have been barr'd and beaten from Publick Worship.</p>
            <p>Therefore this ground is not maintainable, and on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, the Civil Powers are obliged in duty to make all their Subjects perform Publick Worship to God; so that if they had in their Dominions these who worship the Heathen Gods, they ought to punish them if they refuse instruction to worship the true God, and to renounce all Idolatry, they could no more plead Liberty of Conscience, than Murtherers, Robbers, Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers or Sodomites, because the light and law of Nature is no less convincing, the existence of one God absolutely perfect, and that he is to be worshipped, than that these Vices are to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished.</p>
            <p>If they were Mahometans in the Dominions of Christian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, they ought to compel them so far as the light and law of Nature extended, seeing they acknowledge the only one God, and are not Idolaters, yet so as to punish them for any contempt exprest of Christ or the Christian Religion, albeit they did deny that they were perswaded of the truth of it, or used their shifts against the reasons to convince them.</p>
            <p>They might also make the Jews to perform Publick Worship, according to what is reveal'd in the Old Testament acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by them; so that they did not blaspheme Christ or the Christian Religion, albeit they did defend themselves against the reasons adduced for it, and did profess, that they were not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded thereby.</p>
            <p>But none of these ought to be compelled to profess the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Religion, tho' they might be compelled to hear reason for convincing and perswading them to embrace it, but not to make them answer and dispute against these reasons, which yet may be brought in by anticipation, for Christians would not like to be so treated by them, neither is there sufficient evidence of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion, the not answering to the reasons adduced, for many may be puzled that are far from being perswaded.</p>
            <p>It remains then to be considered, what is incumbent to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Soverains in reference to Christian Subjects; wherein it is clear, that they ought to inquire what is the Religion and Way of Worship, most acceptable to God, both for the safety of their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96113:8"/> own Souls and these of their Subjects, and that they are not bound by implicit Faith, or upon the assertion of one Way, or any particular Church, to prefer it to another, without consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and being convinced of the reasons of preference, and whatever Church they chuse they ought to protect and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and to endeavour to have a setled maintainance for the Ministry and Service of that Church, as a part of the Publick Revenue, to be so imployed at their discretion, and they ought to give that Church their just freedom, and may punish such of them as neglect or contemn the Publick Worship of God.</p>
            <p>They may also confirm their Confessions, Canons, and Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, by Law, Sanctions, Priviledges, and Penalties, upon the obstinate disobedience of their own Members, but in every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular to have the judgment of discretion, and should confirm no more than what they judge requisite, although Civil Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies follow Ecclesiastick Censures of course, yet they ought to hear the Complaints of Parties, in order to their Civil Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and consider whether the Church has proceeded according to its Rules and Canons, and if not, to deny their concourse, yet ought they not to hinder their Ecclesiastick Censures to have their intrinsick and proper effect, for that is a part of the liberty of the Church.</p>
            <p>Civil Soveraigns are thus Guardians, Nursing-Fathers of the Church, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Overseers of the Church, as to their own Civil Remedies, which are extrinsick to the Church; but there is no ground thence to pretend, that they are Heads of the Church, or that they can other ways determine of the actings of the Church, but by declaring, that they are free, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less they incroach upon the light and law of Nature, which they ought to punish no less than any other crime, notwithstanding the Judgment of the Church, or if the Church become so cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, that separation from it may be warrantable, they may by the judgment of discretion with the same freedom withdraw their concurse as they gave it, in which case they ought to esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish others as the National Church, and communicate thereto the former Priviledges. They may also call consultative Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Church-men, in order to their Confirmation of the Church, or of their particular Actings, in which they may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed or appoint others to proceed, but cannot warrantably so do in the authoritative Assemblies of the Church, much less can
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96113:8"/> they impose Offices or Ceremonies upon pretence that they are extrinsick to the Doctrine of the Church, seeing the Church it self hath no warrant so to do, much less Civil Authority, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Church had that power it were intrinsick to them.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> may kindly agree, and be mutual helps each to other; the Church ought to teach and exhort, that all due obedience may be given to the Civil Powers, <hi>Honour to whom Honour, Custom to whom Custom,</hi> and <hi>to give Caesar that which is Caesar's,</hi> and <hi>to God that which is God's.</hi> The Church hath an antecedent Judgment in what is by Ecclesiastick Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, but not as to that which is in the proper Commission and Power of the Civil Magistrate. It is an intolerable incroachment of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> upon Civil Authority, that Church-men are not to be punished for crimes, without the antecedent Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, <hi>&amp; nisi tradantur in brachium seculare</hi> though the crime were committed while they are in exercise of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siastical Acts; but their antecedent Judgment is only in order to things intrinsick to the Church, which ought to precede the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinsick determinations of State, which cannot determine Matters of Faith, or any thing intrinsick to the Church, without the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding Judgment of the Church. And, on the other part, the Censures of the Church may be adhibited in the same things which belong to the Civil Authority; they may censure Crimes, but in these the antecedent Judgment belongeth unto the Civil Powers, and the Church ought not to adduce Witnesses to prove Crimes, more than to prove Civil Rights, though upon the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fame of the scandal, they may exclude from Church-Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, but if the party be absolved by the Civil Authority, they ought to acquiesce therein.</p>
            <p>There is no ground to doubt, but God who hath instituted both Civil and Ecclesiastick Authority, would not leave them to clash and interfere, as inconsistent, and therefore they must have their proper limits, tho' they be difficult to be found out.</p>
            <p>The next question is, what is incumbent for the Civil Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in relation to their Christian Subjects that do not submit to the Communion of the National Church. First, then as Civil Authority to cause all their Subjects to worship God so far as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Light or their acknowledg'd Principles will go, there can be no exceptions of Christians as to that point, that they ought not to be hindred, but to be compelled to worship God pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96113:9"/> with some society of Christians, if any such be in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, with which they are free to joyn; if not, it is the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest and will be the Wisdom of Civil Authority, rather to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move such, than to suffer a new Schism to arise, and they may hinder any to exerce the Ministerial Office, who do not profess the Christian Doctrine acknowledged by all National Churches. They may also compel these who acknowledge themselves to be Christians, and know that the Scripture is the Word of God, to profess the popular Confession of these things that are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary for salvation, <hi>necessitate Medii;</hi> against which, there can be no more plea for liberty of Conscience, than against the light of Nature, the authority of both being Divine, and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently necessary, following from acknowledged Principles.</p>
            <p>But if there be Societies of Christians in the same Dominion which hold not communion together, by reason of the peculiar Doctrines, either of the National Church, or of that other So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of Christians, tho' they be not approven of by Civil Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, yet they ought not to be opprest or supprest, but enjoy the freedom of lawful Societies, not only to meet for Publick Worship, but to exerce Government in that way they approve, tho' without assistance of Civil Sanctions, yet so as their disobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Members must ever joyn with some Society of Christians, which are to be tolerated, that all may publickly adore the only true God.</p>
            <p>To apply these Grounds to the particular occurring Cases, for eviting Persecution or Dissimulation and Hypocrisie.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Suppose Soveraign Authority to approve and establish the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> they have no Warrant to compel or persecute the <hi>Reformed Churches</hi> in their Dominions, because all the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof hold all the means necessary to Salvation, and their Ministers hold all the Doctrines acknowledged by all National Churches; and for the same reason they cannot compel or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secute the Churches of the Augustan Confession, albeit they have peculiar Doctrins, seeing these do not pervert the Faith, or overturn the Souls of Men.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the Civil Authority establish a Church of the Augustan Confession, they cannot compel the Reformed Churches in the same Dominion, tho' they keep not communion amongst them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, by reason of their peculiar Opinions about Government, Ceremonies, or Discipline, seeing all of them hold what is requisite for the Members or Ministers of a Christian Church.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:96113:9"/>3. If Civil Soveraigns own and establish a Reformed Church to be the National Church, enjoying the Priviledges and Profits thereof, they ought not to compel or persecute another Reformed Church, differing in Opinions about Government, Ceremonies, or Discipline, nor a Church of the Augustan Confession, tho' they may use all fair means to perswade them fully to unite in one Church, leaving their differences free, or at least to allow mutual communion in Ordinances tho' not in Government, but without constraint.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If Civil Authority establish a Protestant Church, they ought not to compel Papists to conform thereto, but they ought to compel them to perform a Publick Worship of God, forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing these things that are against the light of Nature, as the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipping of any thing which is not God, with religious Worship, directly or indirectly, and particularly the Invocation of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, or of the Souls of Men, of the Hoast at the elevation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in the time of Consecration, or in Processions, (without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring on what account they kneel at receiving) and forbearing the worshipping of Images, Crosses, Reliques, without regard to their coined distinction of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>&amp;</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and therefore they ought not to hinder Priests to perform their Worship in the way it is allowed, yet they ought to exclude Jesuits, and such Fire-brands, as trafficking Seminary Priests, from coming into the Countrey, but only such Parochial Priests as shall be found sober and willing to abstain from the forenamed idolatrous pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices. They may be also compelled to forbear any Doctrin or Practice against the Light of Nature, as Equivocation, Mental Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation, not observing Engagements with these they call <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> or subjecting the Soveraign Civil Powers to the <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Church of Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anabaptists</hi> Churches ought also to have their proper liberty, tho' their Members are not convinced that Infants may be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, yet Infant-Baptism being approven by all National Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, their Ministers should not be tolerate, unless they acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Infant-baptism, wherein they have no reason to complain, for they may find Ministers of that judgment willing to serve them.</p>
            <p>Neither have these of the <hi>Roman Communion</hi> any reason to think they are hardly dealt with, when they consider their cruel persecutions against <hi>Protestants,</hi> but rather should account it an
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96113:10"/> evidence of the true Disciples of Christ, to do good for evil: their Doctrine, as now exponed by the Bishop of <hi>Condam,</hi> and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded by the <hi>Pope,</hi> doth not require worship of Angels, Saints, or Images, and they do forbear Processions where they are tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated in <hi>Protestant</hi> Countries, to evite the scandal of adoring the Host, and therefore cannot refuse to forbear the unnecessary ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation for adoration, which was only introduced by the <hi>Lateran</hi> Council.</p>
            <p>These Sects who pretend to be Christians, and yet deny the evident Principles of Christianity, and will not be baptized <hi>in the Name of the Father, of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost,</hi> or will not acknowledge the <hi>personal Trinity,</hi> and <hi>Unity of the Godhead,</hi> or the <hi>Incarnatian of the Son,</hi> or the <hi>Sacrament of the Eucharist,</hi> they ought either to renounce the name of <hi>Christians,</hi> and profess to be <hi>Heathens,</hi> or <hi>Theists,</hi> as some are now called, or otherwise they ought to be compelled to profess the Doctrins which are the means necessary for Salvation.</p>
            <p>From these grounds proposed, it will easily appear, how far the Liberty of Conscience may warrantably be pleaded, and that it is never to be pleaded against the clear light of Nature, nor by Christians, against these things that are revealed as necessary for salvation, nor by Christian Ministers, against the Doctrins received by all National Churches.</p>
            <p>Besides the Reasons already adduced, for the several Grounds proposed, there are very urgent Reasons for the whole.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is not possible in any other way to shun Persecution, and thereby Hypocrisie and Dissimulation, men professing and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctising against the light of their Conscience, to the dishonour and offence of God, and the ruin of their Souls. The <hi>Church of Rome</hi> (which is not wanting in cunning and policy) found there was no way to keep men under their obedience, without asserting the Infallibility of the Church, and the Duty of Implicit Faith in their determinations, tho' not only beyond, but contrary to the clearest light, by the judgment of discretion, which being obtained, the eyes of their followers were pull'd out, so that without any reluctancy they might be led whither they pleased. With what countenance then can <hi>Protestants</hi> (who have constant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declar'd their abhorrence of Implicit Faith) require any other thing of these of their communion, than what they can clearly convince them of, not by long train of Arguments, but by clear
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96113:10"/> Principles, and immediate Consequences, which will not only puzle, but perswade men, thinking at leisure by themselves, and imploring the aid of God, against prejudice and deception. Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution in <hi>Protestants</hi> is infinitely more pernitious in the persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and more intolerable by the persecuted, being done by these, who in doing of it do not pretend falliblity, and frequently can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pretend evidence and necessity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It doth much reflect upon the wisdom and goodness of God, that having given a Rule of Faith and Manners, by a writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Word, should not have made the things necessary for salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion fully evident; as to the truth of the matter, tho' the manner be mystical in many things, was this omitted, because God could not, or because he would not make what was necessary clear? would he then require, as the common Rule of Christian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, any further than what is necessary and evident.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The design both of God and Man, in setting up Civil Powers, was, that Mens Lives, Liberties and Properties might be better secured than when they were in subordinate Families, can it then be supposed, that any Liberty was so much to be se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured as the Liberty of their Consciences in the Worship of God, whereby they might be free from his Wrath and Eternal Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and might chuse the Way they found safest to save their Souls, and attain Eternal Happ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ness? Was there ever a Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment constituted on these express terms, that all the Subjects should worship whatever Object, and in whatever Manner the Soveraign Power should at option chuse, or impose, and that for disobedience thereto, Subjects should lose their Lives, Liberties, or Estates? Certainly there is no pretence for it from any Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story or Record; yea, if it had been, it could not oblige, because it was not in their power so to ingage, much less can it be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum'd, that the most slavish fear could ever induce men, in their wits, so to ingage themselves and their Posterity.</p>
            <p n="4">4. All Soveraigns do chiefly consider and aim at the plenty and prosperity of their Common-Wealths. If then they compare the condition of the same Countries, while they had no Liberty of Conscience, and when they had it, what a vast difference will they find? that part of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> which, while under the <hi>Spanish</hi> Dominion, and without any Liberty of Conscience, was but the residence of poor Fishermen; since they attained Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Conscience, are now a powerful and plentiful State. <hi>France,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:96113:11"/> while it enjoyed the Liberty of Conscience, was famous and flourishing, now it is become poor and languishing since that Liberty was taken away.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In the present juncture of Affairs, how dangerous, if not destructive were it, to make so great a Body of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants malecontent and disquiet, or even to render peaceable Papists desperate.</p>
            <p>But if the just and fit Measures of Liberty in Religion can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not during this Session of Parliament be adjusted, because of other great Affairs presently urging, it is most necessary, that a Consultative Meeting of Divines, chosen by the seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Communions, should be appointed to meet, and confer upon the best Means to prevent Persecution, before the King, and such as shall be named to assist, by him and the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and that in the mean time, the Penal Laws for Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity should be suspended, at least against Protestants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Grounds here proposed cannot be brangled with, the pretence of venting and spreading Blasphemies and dangerous Doctrins in hidden Conventicles, where they cannot be discovered or anticipated before they raise new Schisms, or that they will encourage all Sects to proselyte setled Churches. For there being none allowed to Preach but these, who approve the Catholick Doctrin of all National Churches, there can be no such danger. And if these be ordained to have stated and known Meeting-houses, it will give no warrant or encouragement to secret Conventicles. It is also specially cautioned, that the arising of new Sects are not to be allowed in Churches where they are not in such number as should be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the liberty of Publick Worship: Nor will the Maintainance of Ministers upon their Congregations Contributions encourage many to withdraw from the National Constitution after a just comprehension; nor any Protestants, but such who dare not, for the peace of their Conscience, serve God in a way whereof they doubt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is not to be imagined, that Protestants will take up the pitiful Pretences used for the <hi>French</hi> Dragoons, from the Master of the Marriage-feast, ordering to compel all on the High-ways to come in, that being but a Parable, and even from the words of it is evident, that it is not a compulsion of force, but of fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent perswasion, or else he that came without the Wedding-garment, could not with justice be bound hand and foot and cast out; much less can the Apostles wish, that they were even cut off that trouble the Church, be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood a cutting off by the Sword, but by Ecclesiastick Censure.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>